<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Francisco Hernandez</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>franciscolhernandez.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="franciscolhernandez.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 02:39:18 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 02:39:18 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Great beginner songs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With enough practice, you can learn any song, even the more difficult ones like &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sI7XiJgt0vY&quot;&gt;Van Halen’s “Eruption”&lt;/a&gt;, but such an advanced song will take a beginner a long time to master. That’s why I would like to suggest a few lists of songs that help beginners with the difficult learning curve. When you are finished with this list, you will notice that learning advanced songs will take less time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are starting out fresh with guitar, I recommend these easy songs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Happy Birthday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jingle Bells&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazing Grace (melody only)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can Can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ode to Joy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or small snippets of popular songs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweet Child O’ Mine - Guns N’ Roses(intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crazy Train - Ozzy Osbourne (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smoke on the Water (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iron Man - Black Sabbath (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One - Metallica (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter Sandman - Metallica (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seven Nation Army - The White Stripes (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today - Smashing Pumpkins (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reptilia - New Hit Song&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also include songs that have easy parts in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/CD-E-LDc384&quot;&gt;Enter Sandman by Metallica&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;img src=&quot;franciscolhernandez.com/assets/img/EnterSandman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Uctu1e353os&quot;&gt;Iron Man by Paranoid&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;img src=&quot;franciscolhernandez.com/assets/img/IronMan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to play easy melodies because you first need to build dexterity and learn how to read tablature. You’ll also want to learn how to position your fingers accurately onto the frets and strum the correct strings. I also included some fun songs with power chords, which are two note chords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel like the first list is too easy, try this list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I Ran (So Far Away) - A Flock of Seagulls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I Wanna Know? - Arctic Monkeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push it to the Limit - Paul Engemann&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zombie - Cranberries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Down Under - Men At Work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Safety Dance - Men Without Hats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eye of the Tiger - Survivor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iron Man - Black Sabbath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paranoid - Black Sabbath (excluding solo)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So Whatcha Want - Beastie Boys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PDA - Interpol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My Own Worst Enemy - Lit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Certain Shade of Green - Incubus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smells Like Teen Spirit - Nirvana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lithuim - Nirvana&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toxicity- System of a Down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self Esteem - The Offspring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sex on Fire - Kings of Leon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Message in a Bottle - The Police&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blitzkreig Bop - The Ramones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All Star - Smash Mouth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I Wanna Be Sedated - The Ramones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hungry Like The Wolf - Duran Duran&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Man Who Sold the World - David Bowie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seven Nation Army - The White Stripes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mr. Brightside - The Killers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today - Smashing Pumpkins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to this level, you’ll be able to play a decent amount of songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll also notice that some hard songs have an easy intro like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2EuPRAMZUY&quot;&gt;“Stariway to Heaven” by Led Zeppelin&lt;/a&gt;, so you can go ahead and learn that part. These songs require a little more dexterity and they all include power chords.  These songs are meant to introduce some basic techniques like palm muting from “Eye of the Tiger”, crescendo which is an increase in volume, and hammer-ons and pull offs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list with a somewhat intermediate difficulty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take On Me - A-ha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snow - Red Hot Chilli Peppers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypnotize - System of a Down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soul Sister - Train (transcribed for Guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pride and Joy - Stevie Ray Vaughn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hotel California - Eagles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thunderstruck - AC/DC (intro)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eruption - Van Halen (finger tapping part)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nothing Else Matters - Metallica (rhythm guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You Give Love A Bad Name - Bon Jovi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cult of Personlity - Living Colour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Man in the Box - Alice in Chains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Float On - Modest Mouse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pretender - Foo Fighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BYOB - System of a Down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suite Pee - System of a Down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kryptonite - Three Doors Down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psycho Killer- Talking Heads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;White Wedding - Billy Idol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dead of Alive - Bon Jovi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last Resort - Papa Roach&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chop Suey - System of a Down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are on this level, you can play most alternative songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More techniques are introduced like bending, sliding, vibrato, alternate picking, and natural harmonics. Songs like “Take On Me” simply have you practice chords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an intermediate list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;La Grange - ZZTop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pinball Wizard - The Who&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carry On My Wayward Son - Kansas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everlong - Foo Fighters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reptilia - The Strokes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free Bird - Lynyrd Skynyrd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Welcome Home - Coheed and Cambria&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dream On - Aerosmith&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…And Justice for All - Metallica (rhythm guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Battery - Metallica (rhythm guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Master of Puppets - Metallica (rhythm guitar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bohemian Rhapsody - Queen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rebel Yell - Billy Idol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roundabout - Yes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tears in Heaven - Eric Clapton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are on this level, you can play pretty much any alternative song and any song that have simple solos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of techniques that are introduced here and almost all the songs are fast-paced, playable and popular. I am also currently on this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that each category increases in speed, so you’ll need more and more dexterity the farther you go down the list. There will be several techniques included for each song, further buiding your guitar skills. In the future, I hope to update this list more so that learning the guitar will be smoother. The important thing is that you practice a lot, build up your playlist, and learn new techniques. I hope this list helps with the difficulty curve and add more your playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 23:39:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>franciscolhernandez.com/beginner-songs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">franciscolhernandez.com/beginner-songs</guid>
        
        
        <category>guitar</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Methods to learn guitar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You might be interested in learning the guitar, but either can’t have enough time for it or don’t know where to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, if you don’t have a guitar, go ahead and buy one. It’s important to have your own instead of having to borrow from someone, because if you have a busy or erratic schedule, your guitar will always be available. If you buy an electric guitar, you might want an amplifier for its distinct sound. Extra effects like distortion pedals can give it the rock-and-roll sound. Alternatively, acoustic guitars have their own crisp sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have a guitar, there are many ways to go about learning it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most obvious methods is to get a guitar instructor. Depending on the instructor, it will usually end with great results because you can learn fundamentals, musical notation, and techniques. This is great, but it’s expensive because guitar lessons are $20-$45 per hour depending on the instructor. Professionals might ask for more than $100 per hour. You might also have a friend that is available to teach you for free. The only problem there is that your friend might not always be available to teach you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a game called Rocksmith made to help beginners learn guitar for the Xbox One, Playstation 4, and PC. If your guitar has an output jack, you connect your guitar with the console and you practice through the guitar songs and slowly progress to mastery. They also include helpful guitar lessons for techniques that you can use in the middle of a song. Although buying the console, the Rocksmith game, and the connection altogether is pretty expensive, it’s a one time payment which is cheaper than the previous method. However, your favorite song might not be in their library, but if you practice with this software enough, your skills can be used to play your favorite song once you learn guitar tablature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you can only buy a guitar or borrow one, one way to learn is simply by practicing your favorite song over and over again until you reach mastery. I recommend starting off with easier songs like “Happy Birthday” just to add some dexterity. Then you can slowly increase difficulty before playing something like Joe Satriani’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F1_ZQoQnI2o&quot;&gt;“Surfing with the Alien”&lt;/a&gt;. Before you do this, you will need learn how to read tablature, which is a form of musical notation that shows how to perform the song. You might need a few pointers about some guitar techniques and fundamentals, but they are readily available on the internet. Additionally, it would be helpful to buy a book on learning guitar, which will help you learn the fundamentals and some basic techniques as well as musical notation like standard notation, which is the notation that all instruments use, and guitar tablature. This is the most affordable method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combination of these three methods would solidify your guitar fundamentals. However, the most important requirement to learn guitar is persistence. You’ll have a difficult start with learning the guitar, but you must continue despite how frustrating it is. Once you pass that difficult learning curve, you’ll enjoy the benefits of guitar mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 21:45:14 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>franciscolhernandez.com/guitar/2017/01/09/methods-to-learn-guitar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">franciscolhernandez.com/guitar/2017/01/09/methods-to-learn-guitar.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>guitar</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
